The דף daf of today's דף daf is קנח Kuf Nun Chet
one five eight and we continue with a series of משניות Mishnayot
no longer about the שכיב מרע shchiv mera on the deathbed bequest
but a series of משניות Mishnayot about houses collapsing on people and
we don't know which order they died and there's a relevance based
on who inherited from whom and in which order. So to remind
us the first משנה mishnah was a father and son and the
question was who died first? Did the father die first and the
property passed through the son and then onto his son onto his
son and therefore by passing through the creditor got liens on it?
Or did the son die first and it went straight to the
son the grandson?
And בית שמאי Beit Shammai as he said in that משנה mishnah
and he's going to say in other משניות Mishnayot basically he says
split it. There's a question if the creditor has rights or not
split it whereas בית הלל Beit Hillel says what seems to us
to be the more reasonable thing which is המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה
hamotzi mechavero alav haraayah that well the phrase בית הלל Beit Hillel
uses is נכסים בחזקתם nechasim bechezkatan they are presumed to be in
the ownership of the one who's in חזקה chazakah of it and
since regardless of which way the property went you know here you
know there's ownership here this is just liens. So clearly it's owned
by חנוך Chanoch and here it's just a question of liens so
you go prove that you have liens since you can't prove it
you're the creditor is out of luck. Okay so that was that
case. Now we're going to look at other cases of houses falling
on people and a question about which order it happened. So let's
take a look at the משנה mishnah on קנח Kuf Nun Chet
עמוד א. amud alef.
נפל הבית עליו ועל אשתו. nafal habayit alav veal ishto. So it's
on a man and his wife. Okay I'll just keep this here
just so that we can
remember this series of cases.
This is עליו ועל בנו alav veal bno this is עליו ועל
אשתו. alav veal ishto. Okay so here's the guy
and here's his wife. Okay fine. Okay now יורשי
הבעל אומרים אשה
מתה ראשונה. yorshei habaal omrim ishah metah rishonah Okay מתה ראשון metah
rishon and afterward the husband died. Now who has the property that
we care about here? The wife does. It's the stuff that she
stole from her father's house. Okay anyway.
Okay so רחל Rachel has the property that we care about. So
here's the story. If רחל Rachel died first they go to יעקב
Yaakov right? So יעקב's Yaakov kids here ראובן Reuven
he says she died first okay she died first went to יעקב
Yaakov from יעקב Yaakov to me. Okay that's what he says. Okay
יורשי הבעל אומרים yorshei habaal omrim אשה
מתה ראשונה ishah metah rishonah. it should be and afterward the husband
died. יורשי האשה אומרים yorshei haishah omrim now the woman's assuming that
she has
ראובן Reuven is from יעקב's Yaakov other wife right? From
לאה. Leah. Okay so he's not a יורש yoresh of רחל. Rachel.
Okay רחל's Rachel other יורשים yorshim okay now let's not let's make
it nice and simple so it's not about competing brothers. רחל Rachel
has no other brother so we're going to have
here's לבן. Lavan.
Okay so alright so לבן Lavan here says so if it went
this way it goes down to ראובן Reuven right? But לבן Lavan
here
says no no no that's not what happened what happened was was
that יעקב Yaakov died first which got him out of the picture
okay and then he's an אלמנה almanah with her property. Once she's
an אלמנה almanah with her property and she dies it goes either
to her kids if she has any or I'm just going to
get it. Okay so which way did it go? Did she die
first and it went to יעקב Yaakov and then to יעקב's Yaakov
kids? Did he die first and get out of the picture and
then she died and it went to her heirs? Okay so is
what they say relevant? Do they? No it doesn't really mean that
they come to court and claim it. It's almost like this is
what they would claim. Right we the בית דין beit din thank
you for raising that question. It really means we the בית דין
beit din have to sit this would be the claim of this
side this would be the you know the possibility that would make
this side win this would be the possibility that would make this
side win. How do we how are we going to determine what's
what? Okay right I mean if one of them actually claims I
was there and I saw it that could be different that's like
a טענת ברי taanat bari but otherwise it's just like a טענת
שמא taanat shema you're just saying this is what I'd like to
say happened. Okay so בית שמאי אומרים יחלוקו Beit Shammai omrim yachloku
that's his standard יחלוקו yachloku that we've sort of seen before it's
not exactly the same thing. reason, but anyway we'll leave it at
that. Here actually maybe it's a better reason. Before it had to
do with an idea that שטרא עומד לגבות כגבוי דמי. shtara omid
ligavos k'gavuy dami. But here anyway you know, so that was hard
because you have a debt it's like it's already collected. Here the
יחלוקו yachloku makes more sense. It either totally went this way or
totally went that way. There's no way of knowing, there's no way
to presume more one direction than the other, okay? And therefore we'll
just split it, okay?
בית הלל אומרים נכסים בחזקתם. Beis Hillel omrim nechasim b'chezkatam. They're in
their חזקה. chazaka. Now what the heck does that mean? Whose חזקה
chazaka are they in? Okay, so that's not at all clear and
the גמרא Gemara is going to have both possibilities for what their
חזקה chazaka means. Does it mean her heirs or does it mean,
you know, does it mean יעקב's Yaakov heirs? But let's, so we'll
get back to that, but then we deal with not the question
of property that she owns, but about the כתובה. kesuba.
Now this is different than סתם stam property that she owns that
we're about to talk about. What we're talking about now is property
that is, you know, the relevance of the כתובה. kesuba. So here
there was a כתובה kesuba and the כתובה kesuba says, you know,
you've got your מנה ומאתים, maneh u'masayim, 100 or 200, you know,
or your תוספת. tosefes. If I die first, says the husband, this
is what you'll get. If you die first you don't get it,
okay? And you have your נכסי צאן ברזל, nichsei tzon barzel,
which basically means property that when we get married, I'm going to
just take into my possession the dowry. If you die first, if
I die first you'll, or we get divorced, whatever, you will take
that property back or I'll give you the value of that property
back, okay? The value was listed here, you'll get the value of
that back, okay? And if you die first I'll, I'll get it,
okay? And then there's the stuff not written in the כתובה, kesuba,
which is נכסי מלוג, nichsei milug, which is the property that she
retains, right? And here he eats the פירות. peiros.
That's the פירות. peiros. Okay, anyway, so, okay, so that's the נכסי
מלוג. nichsei milug. So, what do you do with that property, right?
How do you figure out like who gets what in terms of
all of those various things? Okay, so that's not exactly a question
of inheritance. This is a debt that will be created if he
dies first, right? This is sort of property he's already taken possession
of, but if he dies first she'll get it, okay? This is
property that she owns, but he's getting the fruit, okay? So it's
like sort of what do you do with that? Okay, so let's
take a look. So it says
כתובה בחזקת יורשי הבעל. kesuba b'chezkas yorshei habaal. So the כתובה kesuba
is the 100, 200 and the מאתים. matayim. So this is, you
know, never, it was never her property, and it's a case that
she will have a debt against, like he will owe her money
if he was the first one to die. So we don't know
who the first one was to die. So there's a question if
he ever owed her that money, right? So since there's a question
if he ever owed her that money, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
mechavero alav haraayah. That's not going to get paid. That's like saying
חזקת יורשי הבעל chezkas yorshei habaal means it's not going to get
paid, right? Whose property was it to begin with? What, that he's
bringing in? Oh, she brought it in but... what, this 100 and
200 or this? The 100 and 200 is סתם stam a debt.
If I divorce you or,
or I die first, my estate will pay out to you 100
זוז zuz or 200 זוז. zuz. That's just his own property. That's
his own money, so therefore it's חזקת יורשי הבעל. chezkas yorshei habaal.
It's property of the husband. There's a question if that debt was
ever applied, so forget about it.
Okay, כתובה
בחזקת יורשי הבעל. kesuba b'chezkas yorshei habaal. נכסים הנכנסים והיוצאים עמה, nechasim
hanichnasim v'hayotzim imah, however, the נכסי מלוג, nichsei milug, which she always
retained title to, so since she always retained title to, that's בחזקת
יורשי האב. b'chezkas yorshei haav. That's considered like it's, they never clearly
went over to like this side of the family, it was always
under her control. So it stays within her father's family and it
goes to her יורשים, yorshim, not to his יורשים. yorshim. Now, there
is two things that are questionable here. One is just like it's
not a hundred percent clear why, you know, just because, okay, it
was her property, but like she's a יורש yoresh and he's a
יורש. yoresh. So why do we say חזקת יורשי האב chezkas yorshei
haav means, you know, because it was her property we're more, we'll
assume that her יורשים yorshim got it than his יורשים? yorshim? I
mean it's true, once it gets to ראובן Reuven it's getting away
from her family. But the initial question was because, like, does it
go to, was יעקב Yaakov the יורש yoresh or was לבן Lavan
the יורש, yoresh, right? So it's not exactly clear why we should
more presume it stays within the לבן Lavan family. So תוספות Tosfos
discusses this, and תוספות Tosfos says that he raises two possibilities. One
is that יעקב’s Yaakov inherit,
that יעקב Yaakov a husband maybe only inherits rabbinically. So that so
therefore if we have a doubt, we'll give it to the biblical
line of inheritance rather than the rabbinic. The other explanation he has,
which I think more reflects the language of חזקת יורשי האב, chezkas
yorshei ha'av, it doesn't say
בחזקת יורשי האישה. bechezkas yorshei ha'ishah. חזקת יורשי האב, chezkas yorshei ha'av,
right? So he says it says even if this is a biblical
inheritance, but this is a family. This is קורבה, korva, this is
about blood relation. So therefore, we're going to presume, you know, that
if we had to decide this, go this way or this way,
we're going to keep it within the family rather than transfer it
out of the family. A third way, which is even if there
a variation of this is, this property was given to her when
she got married. In most cases, it was given to her by
her father. It was given to her for the sake of the
dowry and to bring into the marriage. So this is almost like
labeled as your
dowry/father's property. And because of that, unless it's clear that she died
first and the husband took it away, the חזקה, chazaka, the presumptive
ownership of it is the father's ownership, and it's going to stay
on her side of the family. Cause that's נכסי מלוג. nichsei melug.
Now, the question is, okay, so then what when we said the
first line that said הנכסים בחזקתן, hanichasim bechezkatan, right? What is it?
That is it נכסי מלוג nichsei melug that's not נכסי מלוג. nichsei
melug. I mean, we just said that this is property that she
owns,
and here so but what does that phrase בחזקתן bechezkatan mean? So
let's turn the page. Because what we said is, is that this
משנה Mishna says is בחזקת יורשי האב, bechezkas yorshei ha'av, יורשי האב.
yorshei ha'av. The נכסי מלוג nichsei melug it says is, I mean,
יורשי הבעל, yorshei habaal, excuse me. The נכסי מלוג nichsei melug is
בחזקת יורשי האב, bechezkas yorshei ha'av, right? And we sort of said
like, again, it's presumptively his. What does the phrase mean נכסים בחזקתן?
nichasim bechezkatan? First of all, who's what's חזקתן? chezkatan? Whose חזקה? chazaka?
And what נכסים? nichasim? Who's who is the presumptive owner? And which
what are we talking about that we haven't already addressed? I'm sorry,
isn't it why can't it be the משנה הנכסים בחזקתן Mishna hanichasim
bechezkatan and then it's clarifying? Yeah, because so you would have said
that, but the גמרא’s Gemara going to say חזקתן chezkatan has two
interpretations. Either it means יעקב Yaakov or it means לבן. Lavan. And
so it's going to give, right? Which is not the rest of
the משנה. Mishna. The rest of the משנה’s Mishna very explicit, who
gets this and who gets this. But the גמרא’s Gemara going to
say this phrase of הנכסים בחזקתן hanichasim bechezkatan either means יעקב Yaakov
or לבן. Lavan. But it does, it could. No, let's read the
next line of גמרא, Gemara, okay? בחזקת מי? bechezkas mi? Who gets
it? רבי יוחנן אומר בחזקת יורשי הבעל. Rabbi Yochanan omer bechezkas yorshei
habaal. רבי אלעזר אומר בחזקת יורשי האישה. Rabbi Elazar omer bechezkas yorshei
ha'ishah. Okay? ריש לקיש—בר קפרא אמר יחלוקו. amar yachaloku. So they're clearly
not explaining what this phrase of the משנה Mishna means or this
phrase of the משנה Mishna means, they are not debating what the
משנה Mishna might mean פשט. pshat. But they're clearly seeing הנכסים בחזקתן
hanichasim bechezkatan is a third category. Not the נכסי—not nichsei the כתובה
kesubah and not the נכסי מלוג. nichsei melug. Okay? And they're saying
and they have three different interpretations:
יעקב, Yaakov, לבן, Lavan, split it. Okay? וכן תני בר קפרא היו
אלו באים לירש ואלו באים לירש יחלוקו. vechein tani Bar Kappara hayu
elu ba'im liyrash ve'elu ba'im liyrash yachaloku. Split it. Okay, now so
the question is, what are we talking about? We've already addressed the
כתובה kesubah and the נכסי מלוג. nichsei melug. The גמרא Gemara understands
הנכסים בחזקתן hanichasim bechezkatan is some third type of property. And it
has three possibilities what to do with it: יעקב, Yaakov, לבן, Lavan,
or split it. So the so the obvious third candidate is what?
What's the one thing we didn't directly address? Anything gets later on?
No, fine, we'll get back to you in a minute. צאן ברזל.
Tzon barzel. So the רשב"ם Rashbam says we are talking about the
נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei tzon barzel. And that's why it's actually more
complicated. Because
he says, this is property that on the one hand she was
given by her father for the sake of the marriage. On the
other hand, she did not retain title to it. She gave it
to the husband, he took over title, and he just says I
will pay you back its value if I predecease you. So how
do we conceptualize whose חזקה chazaka is that in? More logically, I
would say it's under יעקב’s Yaakov control. He clearly owns it now;
it's a question if he has to give it back. So that's
the argument, it's we assume that it stayed within יעקב Yaakov and
it went down to ראובן. Reuven. The other argument is though, no,
since it was it was like property she got from her father
for the sake of the marriage and he's going to have to
give it back, okay, assuming he does, but whatever, it's always somehow
seen as property that is potentially that is like coming back to
her and like he still has her her name on it. So
it's still is somehow seen as, you know, in the in this
family's control. So that's how he reads that this
is... Whose possession is it in? Is it seen as, is this
נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei tzon barzel seen as in יעקב's Yaakov's possession
or since she got it and she would get, she gave it
to him and she would get it back, it's seen as her
family's possession and the third possibility is יחלוקו. yachloku. Alright, so those
are the sort of three possibilities, although תוספות Tosfos seems to read
נכסים בחזקתם nechasim bechezkatam right, as a more of a possibility of
just like סתם stam property that she owns that wasn't mentioned in
the כתובה, Kesuvah, which is what I think Michael was saying. Okay,
but like so if if the reason for נכסי מלוג nichsei milog
stay within this side of the family here is because she got
it from לבן, Lavan, it was the property she got from לבן
Lavan to bring in and she retained title and so on, okay,
and that stays in it, fine. But how about property she didn't
get from her father? How about סתם stam property that she went
out, she was a smart businesswoman, she invested or she had a
job or whatever, she earned her own property, okay, that makes actually
that fits more the סתם stam question of the משנה. Mishnah. Somebody's
basic property. It's not mentioned in the כתובה, Kesuvah, it wasn't given
at the wedding day to bring into the property, to bring into
the marriage, it's just סתם stam her property. Okay, so that we
could say that's not so clear that should go to לבן. Lavan.
The property לבן Lavan gave her to bring into the marriage and
she retained title to, the נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, that still has
לבן's Lavan's like name on it, okay, but property that סתם stam
she earned,
that's not identified with לבן, Lavan, that's her property. And then the
question is who inherits her property? Should we assume her father inherits
or her husband inherits? So that's why that explains that there's this
three-way debate. One says I don't know, you know, the husband, maybe
he's married so there's a presumptive, he's the presumptive heir, you know,
because whatever, the other says no, maybe לבן Lavan for the reason
I said, you'd rather go with family than with a non-family relation,
or you split it. So that's תוספות's Tosfos's read. תוספות Tosfos seems
to read that this question here is סתם stam property that she
owns, okay. Any property, let's say she like, you know, could be
real- no, I don't mean real estate, okay. I mean anything that
she owns and
that's the debate. So again, what's the case here? There's no way
of knowing which way it went. So as far as the כתובה
Kesuvah stuff goes, okay, whether he has to pay out the כתובה,
Kesuvah, whether there's a debt, it's like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. hamotzi
mechavero alav haraaya. Obviously, he doesn't have to pay out the כתובה.
Kesuvah. The נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, which she brings in to the
property she retains her title to it and it's clearly labeled, like
it's clearly her wedding property, that is going to stay on her
side of the family. That's going to be לבן's Lavan's going to
get. That's the נכסי מלוג. nichsei milog. The נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei
tzon barzel according to the רשב"ם Rashbam or the סתם stam property
that she earns on her own, okay, that stuff where it's easier
to argue both ways. Should we assume that יעקב Yaakov gets it
because, you know, should we assume לבן Lavan gets it? So the
גמרא Gemara has all three possibilities, one the father, one the husband,
and the other is split it. Okay, so that was that. Next
משנה. Mishnah. See, and we already did one דף, daf, one
עמוד. amud. תוספות Tosfos never explicitly spells out that he's reading it
different than the רשב"ם, Rashbam, but if you read the first תוספות
Tosfos בית הלל אומרים נכסים בחזקתם, Beis Hillel Omrim nechasim bechezkatam, it's
implicit throughout that תוספות Tosfos that he seems to be reading it
about סתם stam her property and not about נכסי צאן ברזל. nichsei
tzon barzel. Okay, so let's take a look now at the next
משנה. Mishnah.
נפלה הבית עליו ועל אמו. nefla habayis alav veal imo. Okay, so
you have wife, son, and now or father or whatever and now
you're going to have mother.
רבקה. Rivka. Okay,
נפלה הבית עליו ועל
אמו. nefla habayis alav veal imo. אלו ואלו מודים שיחלוקו. elu veelu
modim sheyachloku. So then the question is, okay,
רבקה's Rivka's the one that's got property.
What order did they die? So יעקב's Yaakov's kids here, ראובן, Reuven,
he says
your wife's here died first,
you inherited from her,
and then you and then dad died and then I got the
property, okay,
whereas רבקה's Rivka's parents, who, בתואל Betuel I guess,
assuming she has no none of her own kids here,
right, that's her father. Anyway, whereas רבקה's Rivka's parents say no, יעקב
Yaakov died first. He was out of the- he was out of
the picture, okay, then רבקה Rivka died, and then it went to,
and then it went to to me, right? It didn't go through
him. Or if you want, right, who's רבקה's Rivka's other son here?
עשו. Eisav. Which- let's make- that's good. Let's have- let's have like
a רשע rasha here, okay? So עשו Eisav could be saying, you
know, my, you know, my- right, my brother died first, okay. Wait,
did I- did I get that right? No, no, no, I was
thinking about it as wife of who inherits from whom, I'm sorry,
I'm sorry. He would inherit from her because it's his mother, okay,
wait, wait, wait. יצחק Yitzchak is- is dead, is out of the
picture, okay? Okay, I'm sorry, I got confused because I was thinking
about wife. If רבקה Rivka died first, and her son יעקב Yaakov
is alive, okay, then her son inherits from her, and then he
dies and passes it on to her grandson. Wait, let's keep יצחק
Yitzchak out of the picture, okay? So gets back to בתואל. Betuel.
I mean, not יצחק, Yitzchak, עשו. Eisav. Let's get back to בתואל,
Betuel, okay? So he would inherit inherit as the son, right, not
as a- okay? Whereas if she has no sons- יעקב Yaakov isn't
alive, okay, and-
and- now wait, why wouldn't the son here get it as her
grandson?
Hold on, let me check the רשב"ם.
Rashbam.
Ah, because here- I'm sorry, okay, so here's the case. The case
is-
yes, because the person here coming to inherit is not יעקב's Yaakov's
son, but is- okay, I don't think רבקה Rivka will work. Let's
do it with רחל Rachel
and ראובן, Reuven, okay, and, so, and then there's
also here
יוסף Yosef and ראובן. Reuven. Okay, there you go. Okay, these two
are brothers, right? But ראובן Reuven is not רחל's Rachel's son. Clear?
So here's the story. יוסף Yosef says- I mean ראובן Reuven says,
רחל, Rachel, my step- my- it's not stepmother, my whatever, yeah, my
stepmother essentially. Anyway, רחל, Rachel, okay, my father's other wife, okay, died
first, יוסף Yosef her son inherited from her, then יוסף Yosef died,
my brother, and I got from יוסף. Yosef. Okay? Yes? So if
my- if my father's other- whatever, if רחל Rachel died first, יוסף
Yosef my half-brother got from his mom, then יוסף Yosef died, he's
my paternal brother, I get from him. What? Assuming יוסף Yosef has
no kids? יוסף Yosef has no kids, okay? Whereas בתואל- ah, not
בתואל here, לבן, Lavan, whereas לבן Lavan says no, יוסף Yosef dies
first, okay, he's out of- so she has no children. She has
no children, I'm going to inherit from her.
Okay? Those are the competing claims, got it? All right, so in
that type of a case, yes, is that clear to people, pretty
much? So in that type of a case, there's no argument like-
as opposed to all of this where was there a debt, was
there not a debt, who- whatever, here nobody has a better claim
than anybody else, right? It's all based on first of all relationship,
it's all based on family, it's not like a husband, which might
be a rabbinic, which isn't family, right? Here was a husband versus
a direct family. No, here it's all a family question, right?
And so how do you know? How do you know if she
died and it went to this line of the family, or he
died first and it went through that line of the family? Okay?
There's no good argument to say one versus the other. So that's
why the משנה Mishnah says, אלו ואלו מודים שיחלוקו, eilue v'eilue modim
sheyachloku, then even בית הלל Beis Hillel and בית שמאי Beis Shammai
agree that you split it, there's nobody that's a presumptive owner in
this
case.
Okay,
what?
ראובן Reuven says- ראובן Reuven says, רחל Rachel died first,
right, my- whatever, my brother's mother died first, okay, so my brother
here, her only son, inherited from her. Then he died, he had
no kids, and now I'm her- his paternal brother and I got
it from him. Whereas לבן Lavan said יוסף Yosef dies first, okay,
he's out of- so she has no children, she has no children,
I'm... I'm going to get from my daughter. Okay. So אלו ואלו
מודים כשיחלקו. Elu ve'elu modim kesheyichalku. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar Rabbi Akiva,
מודה אני בזו, Modeh ani bazo, no in this one I agree,
so the רשב''ם Rashbam says he doesn't really agree but since he's
reflecting the word מודים, modim, okay, he's actually saying the opposite. He
says, you think here everybody agrees? No, actually this one I think
שנכסים בחזקתם shenechasim bechezkatam
that it's not יחלוקו, yachloku, they remain in their חזקה. chazakah. Of
course the question is חזקת מי? chezkat mi? That's the whole point,
there's no clear who's the presumptive owner. So we'll see that in
the גמרא. Gemara. But anyway אמר לו בן עזאי, Amar lo Ben
Azzai, so בן עזאי Ben Azzai said to him, על החלוקים אנו
מצטערים, al hachlukim anu mitzta'arim, it's enough of a like of a
headache that in the earlier cases בית הלל ובית שמאי Beit Hillel
veBeit Shammai were debating, right? Here finally we have a case that
everybody can agree upon. אלא שבאת לחלק עלינו את השוין? ela shebata
lachlok aleinu et hashvin? Finally here everybody agreed and you want to
now say that it's also a debate?
Of course it's a little bit ironic or whatever, you know, pun
because everybody here is agreeing שיחלוקו sheyachloku that you divide it. Right,
יחלוקו, yachloku, מחלוקת, machloket, you want to say that this case is
a, you know, you want to split it. But that's also what
we're saying. We're saying everybody agrees that you split it. I mean,
but he's saying you want to say that we split in terms
of that there's a debate about it. But like it's a funny
use of the language. Yes. Is this רבי עקיבא's Rabbi Akiva language?
Is this also saying המוציא מחברו? hamotzi mechavero? Yeah, I mean, that
phrase in the משנה, Mishnah, בחזקתן bechezkatam is a way of saying
the other side is a המוציא מחברו. hamotzi mechavero. But the question
is, whose חזקה chazakah do you identify it? It's not clear here
what which side should be considered מוחזק. muchzak. That's the whole point.
So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. בחזקת מי? Bechezkat
mi? Who has a חזקה? chazakah? רבי אילא אמר בחזקת יורשי האם.
Rabbi Ila amar bechezkat yorshei ha'em. רבי זירא אמר בחזקת יורשי הבן.
Rabbi Zeira amar bechezkat yorshei haben. Now, thank you very much, those
were the two possibilities, but what's the logic? Okay. So let's take
a look. So כי סליק רבי זירא ki salik Rabbi Zeira when
רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira made עלייה, Aliyah, went up to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, כי סליק ki salik means like when he was עולה,
oleh, it's when you know when he went up to ארץ ישראל,
Eretz Yisrael, קם בשיטתיה דרבי אילא. kam beshitateih deRabbi Ila. He switched
his sides and he wound up going with רבי אילא's Rabbi Ila
that it was חזקת יורשי האם, chezkat yorshei ha'em, okay, that it
was the לבן Lavan here. So קם רבה, Kam Rabbah, now
some cross out this next line. קם רבה בשיטתיה דרבי זירא. Kam
Rabbah beshitateih deRabbi Zeira. Well, since somebody's got to defend the other
side, since רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira switched sides, then רבה Rabbah took
רבי זירא's Rabbi Zeira position to say that it was the son,
you know, בחזקת יורשי הבן, bechezkat yorshei haben, it was ראובן's. Reuven
But anyway, some don't have that line because the next line goes
back to רבי זירא, Rabbi Zeira, the fact that רבי זירא Rabbi
Zeira switched sides. So רבי זירא Rabbi Zeira went to ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael and then he switched sides and he ruled like חזקת
יורשי האם. chezkat yorshei ha'em. אמר רבי זירא, Amar Rabbi Zeira, שמע
מינה אוירא דארץ ישראל מחכים. Shema mina avira de'Eretz Yisrael machkim. That
famous line, ah, now you see it's true, the air in Israel
makes you smart. I went to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and I
realized I was wrong initially, and now I've switched sides and now
I realize that it goes to יורשי האם. yorshei ha'em. So טעמא
מאי? ta'ama mai? So why is it more obvious to you now
that it goes to לבן's Lavan side of the family? אמר אביי,
Amar Abaye, הואיל והוחזקה נחלה באותו שבט ho'il vehuchzeka nachalah be'oto shevet
because the property was sort of came from this שבט. shevet. Okay,
לבן Lavan isn't a שבט, shevet, but it basically means like this
I think here's the situation of arguing. One way of arguing is,
before they got into the same house and the house collapsed, who
was the presumptive heir of רחל? Rachel? יוסף Yosef was the presumptive
heir, right? Everybody was assuming what's going to happen, דרך העולם, derech
ha'olam, the mom's going to die first, יוסף Yosef will inherit her.
He was assuming that he was going to get, so one argument
is, okay, so one way we don't know, he retains his presumption
of being the heir and it goes this way. That presumably is
one side. The other side is, he might have been the presumptive
heir, but the property came from her father's house, had never passed
on anywhere else. Or even maybe if she earned her own property,
right? Well, she earned her own maybe it's a little bit more
questionable. But the point is, is that it's like this is still
property she owns even though she's got a kid and the kid
belongs to a different שבט. shevet. Right? I mean, it's true that
he could be the same שבט shevet by chance. But whatever, you
know, but the kid is like that's sort of it's sort of
like you know the גמרא Gemara like והעברתם את נחלתו, veha'avartem et
nachalato, right? Then when a woman dies the property transfers into like
a different type of an ownership. So here, as long as she
hasn't died, the presumption is is that you know it's not going
to go to her son that has a different type of a
familial... It's let me try to say it this way. It's a
patrimony, right? A patriarchy, excuse me, patrimony, it's a patriarchy. So in
a patriarchy, which family is רחל Rachel a part of? רחל Rachel
is a part of her father's family. So the property as long
as it's in רחל's Rachel possession is part of the patriarchal house
of לבן. Lavan. לבן. Lavan. When she dies, it’ll pass on to
her son, who’s part of a different patriarchal house, his father’s. That’s
what it means, a different שבט, shevet, right? It could be they’re
both the same שבט, shevet, but it doesn’t matter. So the point
is, is that like, is that, you know, it’s like משפחת אב
קרויה משפחה משפחת אם אינה קרויה משפחה, mishpachat av keruya mishpacha mishpachat
em eina keruya mishpacha, right? Which means it’s a patriarchy. So on
the one hand Joseph is the presumptive heir. On the other hand,
as long as Rachel hasn’t died, she’s still part of her father’s
house here. And her husband isn’t alive. If her husband is alive,
you could say she’s an attachment to her husband and that’s the
patriarchal house he’s a part of. But with no living husband, right,
what does the פסוק pasuk say? Her husband dies, והשיבה אל בית
אביה כנעוריה. ve-hishiva el beit aviha kine'ureiha. Okay, I mean, she still
has a son from her husband. But nevertheless, the argument is, with
no living husband, she’s fundamentally part of her father’s house, and you
presume that the property remains under that control. Okay, so two very
interesting ways of looking at it. One which isn’t spelled out: Joseph
is the presumptive heir. The other is, with no living husband, right,
the patriarchal family she’s a part of is this, this is a
different patriarchal family, and you’re going to assume the property is going
to remain in that side rather than the other side. Okay, so
two ways of reading בחזקתה. be-chezkatah. But, but anyway, so within רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva saying that it is not יחלוקו, yachloku, okay, and
that this also was a case of בחזקתה be-chezkatah according to בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, you have both possibilities. But anyway, but the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma says that it’s יחלוקו. yachloku. אמר לו בן עזאי
על החלוקים אנו מצטערים. Amar lo Ben Azzai al hachlukim anu mitzta'arim.
בן עזאי Ben Azzai said, "Oy, you know, it was hard enough
they were arguing about the earlier cases, and here everybody says, agrees,
and you’re going to say they disagree?" So the גמרא Gemara makes
a side point. אמר רבי סימלאי אדע אמרה זאת אומרת, Amar Rabbi
Simlai ada amra zot omeret, בן עזאי Ben Azzai תלמיד חבר talmid
chaver דרבי עקיבא הוה. de-Rabbi Akiva hava. בן עזאי, Ben Azzai, we
know he was a student of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, but after,
you know, a while, you know, he became obviously a major scholar
in his own right, and he was sort of what’s called a
תלמיד חבר, talmid chaver, like a colleague-student. You know, he was, he
gained such sort of status that he was on, you know, that
he was on more equal terms with רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. How
do you know it? דקאמר ליה, Dekamar leh, because when he’s talking
to
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva he says אלא שבאת, ela she-bata, "you came"
to make this a מחלוקת. machloket. He didn’t say שבא רבנו. she-ba
Rabbeinu. You know, he didn’t refer to him in the third person.
The fact that he felt comfortable referring to him in the second
person means that they were on the level of a colleague, a
colleague-student and not just a student. The language is a little familiar
too. "Oh, what are you
doing?" You see the whole sentence. But the גמרא Gemara like, you
know, sometimes in the גמרא Gemara you do have like, you know,
within the sort of love and heat of learning, a little bit
of that like prodding. So the גמרא Gemara isn’t sort of saying
the tone of the whole statement, but it is saying the use
of the second person rather than the third person. Okay, שלחו מתם.
Shalchu mi-tam. So now we’re going to do a completely different thing,
and the only reason we’re going to say this is because it’s
going to tie into an earlier משנה, mishnah, not even this משנה,
mishnah, actually a משנה mishnah that was a few משניות mishnayot earlier.
Some say this whole next גמרא Gemara belongs earlier. Anyway, שלחו מתם.
Shalchu mi-tam. They sent from ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. בן שלווה בנכסי
אביו בחיי אביו. Ben she-lava be-nichsei aviv be-chayei aviv.
A son borrows in his father’s property. Even that whole sentence doesn’t
make sense. What do you mean to borrow in your father’s property?
With a lien against your father’s property? How did you borrow with...
the sentence doesn’t make sense. So we’re going to revise it in
a minute. Okay, so a son that borrows in his father’s property
while his father was alive, ומת, u-met, and then the son
died... oh, the father died. I’m sorry. Okay, the father died according
to this version. בנו, Bno, so this son’s son, מוציא מיד הלקוחות,
motzi mi-yad ha-lakochot, can take the property out of those who purchased
it. So what do you mean he borrowed money and now he’s
taking property from other people? Like what does that mean? וזו היא
שקשה בדיני ממונות. Ve-zo hi she-kasha be-dinei mammonot. And this ruling is
a difficult ruling in דיני ממונות. dinei mammonot. So the גמרא Gemara
says, לווה, lava, one minute, if the son borrowed money, מאי מפקי,
mai mafki, what’s he doing taking property out of other people’s hands?
It’s the other people that should be taking property out of his
hands.
And who even mentioned purchasers? We’re talking about borrowing money. So clearly
this is like a corrupt version of what was said. אלא אי
איתמר הכי. Ela i itmar hachi. Fine, fine, that was a mistake.
Here’s how it was said.
בן שמכר בנכסי אביו בחיי אביו. Ben she-machar be-nichsei aviv be-chayei aviv.
A son sells his father’s property while his father is still alive.
Now the way the רשב"ם Rashbam explains this, what it means is
ראובן Reuven here is assuming, "Hey, I’m going to inherit from Jacob,
from my dad. Let me go ahead and pre-sell my stake in
the inheritance." Now obviously that should be crazy because whatever happened to
like, you know, you can’t, like what do you call it? You
know, it’s like אין אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם, ein adam
makneh davar she-lo ba la-olam, right? I mean, you don’t, you don’t
own yet what you’re going to get from your father. How could
you sell it? Okay, we’ll read it that way for a minute
and then I’ll tell you the way תוספות Tosafot reads it. Okay,
but this is reading it that ראובן Reuven sold the inheritance he
was expecting. expecting to get from יעקב, Yaakov, and he sold it
to, I don't know, to somebody else, to מרדכי. Mordechai. So now
the presumption is that if יעקב Yaakov had died first, then that
sale would be good, and it would pass from יעקב Yaakov through
ראובן Reuven into מרדכי's Mordechai's hands, which is again crazy. Whatever happened
to אין אדם מקנה דבר שלא בא לעולם? Ein adam makneh davar
shelo ba l'olam? Okay,
but that's not what happened. יעקב Yaakov did not die first. יעקב
Yaakov did not die first; ראובן Reuven died first. Okay? So ומית,
U'meis, and he died, בנו מוציא מיד הלקוחות. Bno motzi miyad halakuchos.
So here, let's, let's now that we're done with all these three,
let's have this case. Okay? So here's יעקב, Yaakov,
here's his son ראובן, Reuven,
here's this stranger מרדכי. Mordechai.
He's לקוחות. Lakuchos. What? Here's this property that יעקב Yaakov gets.
ראובן Reuven presells the property to מרדכי Mordechai that he doesn't even
own yet, and the presumption somehow would be that were יעקב Yaakov
to die first, somehow that sale would be good, which is bizarre
and תוספות Tosafos rejects that and we'll get back to תוספות Tosafos
in a minute. Okay, but that's not what happened. What happened was
that ראובן Reuven died first and then and then יעקב Yaakov died.
Okay? No, this was death number one and then death number two.
Fine. And then here חנוך, Chanoch, his son, says, "Hey, listen.
Since when my dad was already dead when my granddad dies here,
my dad never inherited the property. So you don't get that property
my dad sold you because it never went through him. My grandfather
died and I got that property directly. So give me back my
property. Give me..." Okay, so that's what he says. All right? "He's
having a
lien on the property." Right. Okay. The whole thing is crazy. How
is he able to sell? It's not exactly a lien. They're standing
to inherit. But how is he able to sell something he didn't
yet own? Right? But that's what he's saying. Like, "well, maybe if
he was alive, maybe he was giving you the right to take
it from him, but at the end of the day, he didn't
own the property yet and now he's dead and now I get
it." Okay? "Even though he would inherit it." No. Well, right, but
according to this יעקב Yaakov didn't agree to it at all. Okay?
That's along the lines of תוספות. Tosafos. I'll get to תוספות Tosafos
in a minute. Okay? וזו היא שקשה בדיני ממונות. V'zu hi shekasha
b'dinei mamonos. So הגמרא Hagamara asks ולמאי אבוך מזבין ואת מפיק? Ul'mai
avuch mazbin v'at mafik? So the reason it's a difficult ruling is
what's הגמרא Hagamara basically saying? Why can't מרדכי Mordechai say to him,
"I don't get it. Your father sold and you're going to take
it away from me? Like, if your father was more entitled to
that property than you are and if he sold and then it
would be good, like what gives you the right now to stand
in your father's place and to invalidate his sale?" Okay? Which is
presumably why it was קשה בדיני ממונות, Kasha b'dinei mamonos, there something
seems to be unfair about this. Okay? But הגמרא Hagamara says ומאי
קושיא? U'mai kushya? So why is that a problem? דיכול לומר מכח
אבוה דאבא קאתינא. D'yachol lomar mikoch avua d'abba kasina. Sure. I'm getting
it straight from granddad. Okay? It's not going through my father. And
that's why, you know, his sale was invalid, it never went through
him. היכא דכתיב תחת אבותיך יהיו בניך. Heicha d'chasiv tachas avosecha yiheyu
vanecha. In substitution,
you know, to take the place of your fathers will be your
sons. So imagine this פסוק Pasuk is talking to ראובן. Reuven. ראובן,
Reuven, the person that will come to take the place of your
father יעקב Yaakov will be your son חנוך, Chanoch, which means the
grandson takes the place of the grandfather. תשיתמו לשרים בכל הארץ. Tishisemo
l'sarim b'chol ha'aretz. To make them as officers of the whole land.
Anyway, so he says אלא. Ella. So fine. That makes total sense.
So then why is it קשה בדיני ממונות? Kasha b'dinei mamonos? It's
completely legitimate that חנוך Chanoch is saying, "You know, you never got
it, my father never got it." אלא אי קשיא הא קשיא. Ella
ei kashya ha kashya. Fine. Here's what it means קשה בדיני ממונות.
Kasha b'dinei mamonos. Meaning the problem here is that the message שלחו
מתם Shalchu misam was, "this is the ruling, but it's a really
difficult ruling." Like, it goes against logic. So הגמרא Hagamara says, this
would make sense, that חנוך Chanoch could take it from מרדכי, Mordechai,
but we wouldn't use the phrase קשה בדיני ממונות. Kasha b'dinei mamonos.
That would actually be a reasonable פסק. Psak. So what is the
ruling that that we should say this is the legal point but
it doesn't make sense? So אלא אי קשיא הא קשיא. Ella ei
kashya ha kashya. This would be the difficult ruling. בן בכור שמכר
חלק בכורה בחיי אביו. Ben bechor shemachar chelek bechorah b'chayei aviv. That
actually ראובן Reuven here's the בכור Bechor
and he didn't just sell סתם Stam his חלק. Chelek. Okay, he
sold the second portion, okay, this is the second portion, חלק בכורה.
Chelek bechorah. That's what he sold. Okay, so
of that's what he sold, בן שמכר חלק בכורה בחיי אביו, Ben
shemachar chelek bechorah b'chayei aviv, ובנו מוציא מיד הלקוחות, U'veno motzi miyad
halakuchos, וזו היא שקשה בדיני ממונות. V'zu hi shekasha b'dinei mamonos. Now
this is difficult, because what entitles חנוך Chanoch to this extra portion?
חנוך Chanoch can't just say, "Hey, I'm getting it straight from granddad.
Forget dad." Okay? My grandfather died and my father wasn't alive and
it came straight to me from
grandad. No. So if you're standing in your father's place to get
it, so the same thing that entitles you to the בכורה bechorah
portion should mean that the sale should go through. You're playing ראובן's
Reuven's role. So if the sale if it would have passed through
if ראובן Reuven was alive and now you're clearly in the position
of son, not grandson to get the double portion, so then that
should then it should continue on to מרדכי. Mordechai. That actually makes
sense, right? By whatever virtue if יעקב Yaakov had died first it
would have gone on to מרדכי, Mordechai, you now are playing your
father's role. You are not here as grandson, you are here as
son because you're claiming the חלק בכורה. chelek bechorah. Okay, so that's
what he says. So in that he says,
ומת הבן ובניו מוציאין מן הלקוחות. u-mes haben u-vanav motzi'in min halekuchos.
Nevertheless, he can take the בכורה bechorah חלק chelek away from מרדכי.
Mordechai. וזו היא שקשה בדיני ממונות. v'zu hi shekasha b'dinei mamonos. Because
here's why it's קשה. kasha. אבוה מזבין ואי
מפיק? avuha mazbin v'ee mafik? So because that's why it's קשה, kasha,
because he says what type of how's this fair? Your father sold
and you're coming now to take it away from me? And now
the גמרא Gemara says, wait a minute. וכי תימא הכא נמי אמר
מכוח אבוה דאבא קאתינא? ve-chi teima hacha nami amar mikoach avuha d'abba
ka'asina? Oh no, this makes sense. I'm just getting it straight from
granddad. But no! אי מכוח אבוה דאבא קאתינא בחלק בכורה מאי עבידתיה?
ee mikoach avuha d'abba ka'asina b'chelek bechorah mai avidtei? No,
if you were getting it straight from granddad, you wouldn't have a
right to the בכור bechor portion. So if you're claiming a right
to the בכור bechor portion, it's because you're standing in for your
father, and if you're standing in for your father, I should get
it. That makes a lot of sense, okay? If we assume this
sale was good to begin with, which who knows why, but if
we assume that, I should get it. So the גמרא Gemara now
says, so to me that makes a lot of sense, I don't
really understand the גמרא's Gemara's response. The גמרא Gemara says, ומקשי, u-makshi,
why is that a problem? דאמר מכוח אבוה דאבא קאתינא, d'amar mikoach
avuha d'abba ka'asina, I'm getting it straight from granddad, ובמקום אבא קאימנא,
u-vimkom abba ka'imna,
but I'm standing in my dad's place. Like what? What does that
mean? I'm getting it from my granddad so it bypasses my father,
but I'm getting it in the role of my father. I don't
understand. I mean the רשב"ם Rashbam did not help me here. Since
you have to say I'm standing in my father's place to get
the חלק בכורה, chelek bechorah, then it should logically pass on to
you. I don't understand the גמרא's Gemara's retort to this. Anyway, but
that's the basic way the גמרא's Gemara's saying it. Now I'll just
say one sentence about תוספות. Tosafos. תוספות Tosafos says none of this
makes sense. ראובן Reuven cannot pre-sell his portion. So what תוספות Tosafos
says we're talking about is not סתם stam a ירושה, yerushah,
but what the גמרא Gemara did was that יעקב Yaakov said while
יעקב Yaakov was still alive he said he gave the גוף guf
to ראובן Reuven and he kept the
פירות. peiros. Remember we've had that before, that a father when he's
alive could sort of say I'll continue to benefit it but I'm
transferring the actual גוף guf to you right now. Okay, now that
doesn't work so well with the חלק בכורה chelek bechorah because then
it's just like
an actual property ownership. But according to that, the reason חנוך Chanoch
can come and take it away is because the sale really to
ראובן Reuven did not go through until ראובן Reuven came
to, to מרדכי, Mordechai, until ראובן Reuven came into full possession. Had
יעקב Yaakov died first and then he would have come into full
possession it would have gone on. תוספות. Tosafos. But because יעקב Yaakov
did not die first and ראובן Reuven never came into full possession,
okay, so in that type of a case חנוך Chanoch says I
inherited it, that sale never took place, I'm taking it away. Okay,
so it's a little like forcing a read into the גמרא, Gemara,
but תוספות Tosafos is very reasonably bothered with how the heck do
you pre-sell a portion in your inheritance? Okay, so that's where we
are, we will continue trying to figure out different variations of what
קשה בדיני ממונות kasha b'dinei mamonos means tomorrow.